Finding Aid for Joseph T. A. Lee papers, 1964-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph T. A. Lee papers
1964-1990
Lee, Joseph T. A.
0686 Aa 2 UAm
Joseph T. A. Lee was an Ann Arbor architect and Professor in the University of Michigan School of Architecture; chair of the steering committee for the Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference. He was one of the original owners of Kerrytown Market as well as its chief architect. Lee was also involved in several Ann Arbor development issues, including the debate over the Geddes-Fuller corridor. His papers include administrative and financial materials on the early development of Kerrytown (1966-1980) and clippings and other materials on his involvement in the Geddes-Fuller corridor debates. His papers also include architectural drawings of the Kerrytown Townhouse and Kerrytown Market Complexes as well as some photographs of early Kerrytown development.
2.5 linear feet
266 oversize folders
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Joseph T. A. Lee (donor no. 9632 ) in August 2005 and January 2007.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Joseph T. A. Lee was an Ann Arbor architect and Professor in the University of Michigan School of Architecture. He was one of the original owners of Kerrytown Market as well as its chief architect. Lee was also involved in several Ann Arbor development issues, including the debate over the Geddes-Fuller corridor.
In 1966, Joseph T. A. Lee along with Arthur E. Carpenter, Ann Arbor lawyer, and John E. Swisher, Ann Arbor realtor, proposed redeveloping lots on South First between Jefferson and Madison. The Kerrytown project, as it was named, aimed to replace existing structures and build new townhouses and low and high rise apartments. While the Kerrytown Townhouse Complex was never built, this proposed residential development was catalytic in the founding of the city's historic preservation movement, as citizens created the Old West Side Historic District in order to protect the late nineteenth and early twentieth-century buildings, which the Kerry town Townhouses would have replaced.
In 1967, Lee, Carpenter, and Swisher formed Arbor-A, Inc. a corporation dedicated to redeveloping city areas. Arbor-A was involved in several projects, including the development of the Kerrytown Market Complex, an adaptive re-use development, which has become one of the important hubs of Ann Arbor's retail community, while preserving the historic character of this old neighborhood.
Lee was also involved in several Ann Arbor development issues and discussions. He was chair of the steering committee for the Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference, held January 25, 1966. The conference met to discuss and establish goals for the rapidly changing physical environment of Ann Arbor and surrounding area. Lee was also involved in the debates concerning the Geddes-Fuller corridor. In the 1960s and 1970s, the city became increasingly concerned with the ability of the Geddes-Fuller corridor to handle future traffic. The University of Michigan wanted to widen the Geddes-Fuller corridor to four lanes and extend the corridor to US-23 to allow better access to the new Hospital. Citizen's groups (of which Lee was a part) argued that the widening would negatively affect the surrounding environment.
The debate over the Fuller-Geddes corridor surfaced again in 1994 when the City of Ann Arbor, the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority, the University of Michigan, and Ann Arbor Township led a study on the Fuller-Geddes-Conrail corridor to examine the potential future traffic problems in this area.
The Joseph T. A. Lee papers include administrative and financial materials on the early development of Kerrytown (1966-1981) and clippings and other materials on his involvement in the Geddes-Fuller corridor debates. His papers also include architectural drawings of the Kerrytown Townhouse and Kerrytown Market Complexes as well as some photographs of early Kerrytown development.
The Lee papers have been divided into three series: Kerrytown Projects, Other Ann Arbor Projects, and Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference.
Subjects:
Lee, Joseph T. A.; City planning--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Kerrytown (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Arbor-A, Inc.; Roads--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Highway planning--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference.
Contributors:
Arbor-A, Inc.; Clay, Grady.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Kerrytown Projects, 1966-1981
  The Kerrytown Projects series (1 linear foot and 266 drawings, 1966-1981) consists of working files and drawings.
  - Working files
    Included in the working files are initial proposals for the Kerrytown Townhouse complex as well as various proposals, correspondence, and financial information on the development of the Kerrytown Market Complex. This subseries also contains administrative materials on the Arbor-A, Inc. corporation, including financial records and meeting minutes of the Board of Directors and Stockholders.
    - 500 Detroit Street Project (gas station), 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Arbor-A, Inc.
      - Administrative, 1969-1979; 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Arthur Carpenter correspondence, miscellaneous, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      - Bylaws, 1967 (Box 1)
      - Calvert Fish Market (eviction), 1977 (Box 1)
      - Logo, undated (Box 1)
      - Meeting minutes (Board of Directors, Stockholders), 1967-1980 (Box 1)
    - Chronology (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1966-1981 (Box 1)
    - Market complex
      - Arbor-A accounts, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
      - Consultation services (phase I), 1970 (Box 1)
      - Drawings, 1971; undated (Box 1)
      - Electrical/gas, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
      - Market Town, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
      - Muschenheim, Hammarskjold & Arms, Inc. Architects-Planners, 1970 (Box 1)
      - O'Neal Construction contract (phase I), 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - Tenant accounts, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
      - Tenant stalls and codes, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
      - Warehouse space rental survey, [, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1970s; undated (Box 1)
      See also oversize folder UAm
    - Townhouse complex Proposals, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Drawings
    The Drawings subseries (266 drawings, 1969-1976 and undated) encompasses 266 architectural drawings of two of Joseph Lee's important projects in Ann Arbor: the Kerrytown Townhouse Complex (never built) and the Kerrytown Market Complex. The 261 Kerrytown drawings of the market complex document the evolution of the development, including the schematic design, design development and construction phases, which began in 1969.
    - Kerrytown Townhouse Complex, Ashley and Madison Streets, Ann Arbor, Michigan
      - Preliminary Site Plans Showing Phases of Project by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, undated; 5 items blue-line prints (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
    - Kerrytown Market Complex, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1969-1976
      - Alterations of Roach Building
        - Design Development and Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 6/18/1969-2/27/1971; 31 items twenty-three drawings on vellum and tracing paper and eight blue-line and sepia prints with pencil and ink notations (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
      - Proposed Development of Arbor-A Indoor Market Complex
        - Presentation Site Plans, Elevations and Renderings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 1/19/1970-5/1971; 16 items nine pencil drawings on-vellum and-tracing paper and seven blue-line prints with marker coloring (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
        - Preliminary Architectural Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, and Muschenheim, Hammarskjold & Arms, Inc., Associated Architects, 5/11/1970-5/25/1970; 5 items blue-line prints with pencil notations (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
      - Arbor "A" Indoor Market (South) Building
        - Preliminary Architectural, Mechanical and Electrical Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, 6/15/1970; 15 items seven pencil-on-vellum drawings and eight blue-line prints ("Office Copy") with pencil notations (Map-case 1, Folder 5)
      - Market Buildings "A" and "B"
        - Preliminary Planning Studies by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 8/1/1970-9/9/1971; 50 items twenty-one pencil drawings on vellum and tracing paper and twenty-nine blue-line and sepia prints with pencil and ink notations (Map-case 1, Folder 6)
        - Design Drawings Showing Sequence of Development by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 6/20/1970-7/13/1970; 9 items two pencil-on-vellum drawings and seven blue-line, sepia and mylar prints with pencil notations (Map-case 1, Folder 7)
        - Preliminary Planning Studies by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 1/4/1971-6/30/1971; 9 items three pencil-on-vellum drawings and six blue-line prints with pencil notations (Map-case 1, Folder 8)
      - Stage I Alteration of (South) Building "A"
        - Architectural, Structural, Mechanical, Electrical and Landscape Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, and Robert M. Darvas & Associates, Consulting Structural Engineers, 8/26/1970-5/18/1971; 45 items twenty-one pencil drawings on vellum and tracing paper and twenty-four blue-line prints ("Office Set") with pencil notations (Map-case 1, Folder 9)
      - Alteration of (North) Building "B," Stage 2-A (not used)
        - Design Development and Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A Lee, Architect, 8/7/1971-11/3/1971; 40 items thirty pencil drawings on vellum and tracing paper and ten blue-line and sepia prints with pencil and ink notations (Map-case 1, Folder 10)
      - Market Shop Tenants
        - Design Development and Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 6/1/1970-8/1/1976; 35 items twenty-six pencil drawings on vellum and tracing paper and nine blue-line and sepia prints with pencil notations (Map-case 2, Folder 1)
      - Market Parking and Signage
        - Construction Drawings by Joseph T. A. Lee, Architect, 6/28/1971-10/12/1972; 6 items five pencil-on-vellum drawings and one blue-line print with ink notations (Map-case 2, Folder 2)
- Other Ann Arbor Projects
  The Other Ann Arbor Projects series (0.5 linear feet, 1964-1994) includes clippings, reports, and concerned citizen letters about the Geddes-Fuller corridor proposals in the 1960s and 1970s as well as material on the 1994 Geddes-Fuller corridor study. Administrative information on miscellaneous environmental groups, including the Southeast Michigan Environmental Action Council, Washtenaw Environmental Action Council, and the Huron River Beautification Committee can also be found in this series.
  - Fuller-Geddes corridor
    - 1964-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous materials, 1966-1978 (Box 2)
  - Geddes/Fuller/Conrail corridor
    - Citizen's Advisory Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Final report: Geddes/Fuller/Conrail Corridor Study, July 1994 (Box 2)
  - Huron River
    - Huron River Beautification Committee of Ann Arbor Township, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Huron River Recreation Resource Study, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Southeast Michigan Environmental Council (bylaws), 1971 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw Environmental Action Council, 1971 (Box 2)
- Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference
  The Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference series (1 linear foot, 1965-1969) includes steering committee minutes and planning materials, keynote address given by Grady Clay, notes from conference workshops, post-conference materials; also files of Lee's activities with the later Ann Arbor Ad Hoc Goals Committee, 1969.
  - Steering Committee meetings and pre-conference planning materials, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Steering committee planning materials and local arrangements, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Conference remarks, programs, roster, etc., 1966 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Grady Clay keynote address (with information about Clay), 1966 (Box 3)
  - Workshop notes, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Post-conference materials (including Quo Vadis Ann Arbor?) (Box 3)
  - Steering committee, post-conference, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Review of conference, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Pre-conference, communication with other cities, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Materials from outside cities, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Proposed Ann Arbor Metropolitan Citizens Council, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor Ad Hoc Goals Committee, 1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Publications (Box 3)